Guide to the New York City Immigrant Labor History Project Oral History Collection OH.014
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- New York City Immigrant Labor History Project
  - Hochberg, Eddie, 1975 March 3 (Box Access Cassettes, Cassette 112a-b, Box 24, Reel 88a, Box 25, Reel 88a - 88b, Box 100, Cassette 88a - 88b)
    This interview was conducted at the Workmen's Circle Home for the Aged in the Bronx, New York on March 3, 1975 by David Lightner. The main topics include Eddie Hochberg's life in Russia; his immigration to the United States (US); his work in the garment industry both in Russia and the US; and the internal organization of garment workers' labor unions in New York, New York. Hochberg discusses his early life in Russia, including his family's poverty and his father's work as a supervisor in a logging company. He discusses the immigration of his family to the US, including his father immigrating in 1911 and finding work in a paper box factory; two of his brothers immigrating after their father; Hochberg immigrating alone in 1914; and the rest of his family following in 1916. He describes finding his first job through a man with whom he attended synagogue; not being paid for three weeks while he learned the trade; and his first job turning over coats to create seams. He discusses his movement through different factories within the garment industry and his work in each, including manufacturing coats for men, cloaks, and dresses; being paid for both week work and piecework; cleaning and oiling the machines every Friday; working overtime during the busy season; and having to find other employment during the summer. He describes the introduction of labor unions into the garment industry, including the fact that very few companies were unionized initially; the establishment of the National Recovery Administration in 1933 guaranteeing workers the right to join unions; that different locals within the same international union being determined by profession as well as ethnicity; and unions providing benefits such as better pay, vacations, and pensions. Hochberg also mentions that he was a member of multiple unions, including the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union Local 22, the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, and the United Brotherhood of Cloak Makers Local 1.
    International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 22 (New York, N.Y.); United Brotherhood of Cloakmakers
  - Hoffman, Simon, 1974 April 4 (Box Access Cassettes, Cassette 57, Box 97, Reel 904a - 904b, Box 1, Folder 42)
    Simon Hoffman was born in Pilviskiai, Russia in 1893 to a Jewish family. His father worked as a butcher and his mother worked as a wig maker. Hoffman immigrated to the United States (US) through Ellis Island in New York, New York in 1913. He briefly lived with his step-siblings in the Bronx before finding a job as a cap maker. During the Great Depression, Hoffman was employed by the City of New York cleaning public parks. He became a US citizen and a member of the Democratic Party in 1920. He continued to work in the cap making industry until his retirement. He was a member of an unspecified cap makers' union (likely the United Hatters of North America).
    This interview was conducted by Suzanne Michel at the Bialystoker Home for the Aged in Manhattan, New York on April 4, 1974. The main topics discussed include Simon Hoffman's life in Russia; his immigration to the United States (US) and his early days there; his work in New York, New York; and leisure activities in which he participated. Hoffman discusses his early life in Russia, including the fact that he learned four languages despite not attending school; his work selling sewing notions; and the fact that the Jewish community mixed with other local ethnic groups for commerce but were otherwise segregated. He recalls his family, including the fact that his father was a butcher and was substantially older than his mother; that his mother regretted marrying an older man; his mother's work manufacturing wigs and hairpieces; and his three siblings. He discusses his immigration to the US, including paying a smuggler 25 rubles to help him cross the border between Russia and Germany; sailing on the SS Bremen from Bremen, Germany; being assisted by the Hebrew Immigrant Aid Society after his arrival at Ellis Island, New York; and residing with his step-siblings in the Bronx for a short time before finding work. Hoffman recalls his employment in the US, including making hats on Houston Street in Manhattan; receiving a pay increase during World War I; being employed by the City of New York to clean public parks during the Depression; and resuming his employment in the cap making industry in 1942. He mentions joining an unspecified cap makers' union (likely United Hatters of North America) in 1915, and was proud of the fact that he maintained his union membership after his retirement. Hoffman discusses his leisure activities, including reading the New York Times, the Jewish Daily Forward, and the Jewish Morning Journal; visiting the Hayden Planetarium at the Museum of Natural History in Manhattan; and attending the Jewish theater frequently.
    Depressions |y 1929 |z New York (State) |z New York.; United Hatters of North America
  - Hoffzimmer, [Unknown], 1973 April 12 (Box Access Cassettes, Cassette 18, Box 25, Reel 90a - 90b)
    The narrator's first name is unknown. Mr. Hoffzimmer was born in present day Poland in 1896 to a Jewish family. He immigrated to the United States in 1909 and attended public school in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. He was employed making human hair goods and Panama hats and opened his own hat manufacturing company before the Great Depression. Hoffzimmer was an active member of the Socialist Party of America and the United Hatters of North America.
    This interview was conducted by Karin Young on April 12, 1973 at the Sheltered Workshop of the National Council of Jewish Women in Manhattan, New York by an unknown interviewer. The first name of the narrator is unknown. Mr. Hoffzimmer reminisces about his early life and immigration to the United States (US), including his father being a cobbler; his father not teaching him the trade; and falsifying his immigration papers to show that he was 16 years old in order to emigrate. He discusses the immigration process at Ellis Island, New York, including a required medical examination; the requirement of either $25 or someone to vouch for you; and immigration societies that would vouch for individuals who knew no one in New York and assist them with acquiring lodgings. His first impressions of New York City include not feeling excited about living in New York; the abundance of poverty; and hostilities between ethnic groups, especially between the Jewish and Irish communities. He discusses his involvement with Socialism and the Socialist Party of America, including attending lectures and meetings at the Rand School of Social Science in Manhattan; his feelings about Social Security; society's lack of appreciation for social programs at the time of the interview; and reading the Socialist newspaper The New York Call. Hoffzimmer discusses his family, including meeting his wife through friends; and sending his daughter to the Workmen's Circle to learn about Jewish language and culture. He discusses his great appreciation for his wife; and the accomplishments of his grandson. He recalls his work experience, in particular finding employment as a hatter through his work manufacturing human hair goods. He describes traveling to the western US and to Mexico with the money he saved at his first job. He recounts learning Spanish and opening a business selling portraits while in Mexico; and opening his own hattery upon his return to New York with the money he made. He also recalls not requiring government assistance during the Great Depression because of his business; discusses the benefits and drawbacks of modernization; and discusses his membership in the United Hatters of North America.
    Jewish socialists -- New York (State) -- New York -- Interviews.; United Hatters of North America; Workmen's Circle/Arbeter Ring
  - Howard, Clara, 1973 April 20 (Box No Master)
    Clara Howard was born in Hampton, Virginia on September 13, 1895. She was one of ten children. Her mother managed the household and her father was farmer and firefighter. Her husband was born in a rural part of Virginia. He served in the United States Navy, worked for the United States Postal Service, and owned a jewelry and watch repair business in White Plains, New York. They married in 1912 and had three children.
    This interview was conducted by Edmund Lake at the Council Workshop for Senior Citizens on 125th Street in Manhattan, New York on April 20, 1973. The interview covers Clara Howard's early life in Hampton, Virginia; her family; and her opinions on racial discrimination and civil rights in the United States. Howard discusses her education at the Gray School of the Hampton Normal and Agricultural Institute in her hometown, which she attended through the tenth grade. She describes her family's home and explains that although they lived on a farm, they were near large cities, including Newport News and Norfolk, and did not live in an isolated area.
    Howard explains that her older sisters migrated to New York and New Jersey and that she decided to migrate to New York when she was 16 years old after visiting. She recounts living on 139th Street in the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan with her sisters in 1912; explains that African Americans were starting to move into Harlem at that time; and describes Harlem as beautiful, brightly lit, and clean. She compares the living situation of minorities in downtown Manhattan to those in Harlem and her belief that the conditions downtown were more primitive than those in Hampton. She compares her children's education to her own and discusses her opinion that she received a much better education as her teachers were black, took great interest in their students, and served as role models. She recounts an incident of racial prejudice one of her children experienced, her reaction to it, and her feeling that this exemplified the failing of the educational system in New York.
    Howard discusses Marcus Garvey, Father Divine, Martin Luther King, Jr., and Malcolm X, and describes them as great men. She recounts attending services and lectures at the Abyssinian Baptist Church in Harlem. She discusses black empowerment, including black leaders encouraging the people to pull themselves up but not providing them with the tools to do so and her feeling that most people lack the desire for education. She describes her pride in her education; her willingness to defend herself and family against racial discrimination and injustice; her amazement at the fact that so few people in her community were unwilling to make a similar stand; and her willingness to die for her beliefs.
    Howard discusses her husband's first job with the United States Postal Service (USPS); the racial segregation within the USPS that led to his unhappiness; and his decision to start his own business. She discusses her husband's jewelry and watch repair business in White Plains, New York, including the fact that the majority of his customers were white; his belief that his religious faith had enabled him to open his own business; and her management of the shop after he was injured in a car accident.
    Other topics include leisure activities and holidays; theaters in Harlem, including the Alhambra; and Howard's enslaved grandparents who fled their owners before their two oldest children could be sold away from them.
    See also: Council Workshop for Senior Citizens II.
  - Hyman, Bella, Undated (Box Access Cassettes, Cassette 59, Box 98, Reel 908a - 908b, Box 1, Folder 43)
    Bella Hyman was born in a small town in Austria in the late 1890s. She was one of nine children. Her parents owned a small grocery store, her father studied in the synagogue, and her mother catered events in the town. Hyman immigrated to the United States (US) in 1913. Her parents and two of her brothers immigrated to the US in 1921.
    She worked in the garment industry in the US, as a hand sewer and finisher. She was a member of an unspecified union (likely the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union). She married in 1923 and had one son. Her husband was born in Russia and immigrated to England when he was young. He was educated in England and was a lecturer. In the US, he was a manager of an unspecified union local. He died in 1940. She and her husband belonged to the Socialist Party of America and the Workmen's Circle.
    This interview was conducted by Janice Albert. The date and location of the interview are unknown. The interview covers Bella Hyman's childhood in Austria, her working life in the United States (US), and her union activity.
    Hyman discusses attending night school in the US; participating in organizing garment factories for the union (likely the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union); and wishing she could have continued her education but having to work in order to pay for her parents' immigration to the US. She recounts her childhood in a small town in Austria, including her education and her father studying in the synagogue while her mother managed the family's grocery store and catered events in the town. She describes her and her siblings' immigration to the US; their consolidation of their savings in order to pay for their parents' immigration; and the family's struggles during the Great Depression.
    Hyman discusses her life in New York, New York after her immigration, including gaining experience in garment factories through different jobs, and moving between different Jewish neighborhoods in Manhattan, Brooklyn, and the Bronx. She recounts wanting to become a nurse; starting a training program at Beth Israel Hospital in Manhattan; and having to leave the program because it did not pay enough for her to contribute to her parents' immigration. She discusses attending night school and lectures at the Rand School of Social Science in Manhattan; being inclined towards the Socialist Party of America; and finding time to attend dances and sporting events. She describes the ethnic demographics of the workforce in the garment industry, in particular, the fact that the workers were mostly Jewish, Italian, and Polish, which led to language issues while organizing the factories into an unspecified union (likely the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union). She describes the daydreams the garment workers would share with each other and the songs they sang while they worked, but states that these hopes did not preclude their participation in unionizing efforts in order to improve working conditions.
    Other topics include her work visiting retired union members; the movement of the garment industry from the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan to 7th Avenue in the Midtown neighborhood of Manhattan; her husband's background; and women in leadership roles in unions, specifically Rose Pesotta and Pauline Newman.
    Summary and index are available for this interview.
    See also: Ethnicity, and Family.
    Women socialists |z New York (State) |z New York.; Workmen's Circle/Arbeter Ring
  - Icolari, Alfonso, Undated (Box Missing, Box 1, Folder 96)
    Alfonso Icolari was born in Faggiano, Italy in 1898 and was one of five children. He immigrated to the United States (US) with his family in 1910 and settled in the Ocean Hill neighborhood of Brooklyn, New York. He attended school up to the seventh grade. He worked as a farmer in Italy. In the US he worked as a shoe shiner and in an unspecified capacity at the Brooklyn Navy Yard; Borden, Inc.; the Brooklyn-Manhattan Transit Corporation (BMT); and the Long Island Railroad (LIRR) in the US.
    The audio recording for this interview is missing. Currently all that is available is Icolari's interview fact sheet, which contains only the biographical information recorded in the Biographical Note.
  - Immigration, Migration, and First Impressions of New York, New York and the United States, Undated (Box Access Cassettes, Cassette 245, 245a, Box 13, Reel 38a - 38b)
    This recording contains excerpts of different interviews, all of which focus on discussions of immigrants' and migrants' first impressions of the United States (US) and New York, New York. The volume and sound quality of this recording fluctuate between excerpts. The excerpts cover reasons for immigration or migration; conditions during immigration, including memories of Ellis Island; and the living situation of relatives before and after immigration or migration. They cover assimilation struggles, including racial and ethnic discrimination in the US; the differences in treatment of different immigrant groups by American citizens and other immigrant groups; struggles to learn English and acquire citizenship; and deportation of immigrants during wartime. Other topics relate to life in the US, including education; a comparison of the US and the immigrants' and migrants' places of origin including living conditions, working conditions, food, weather, and architecture; the mythology surrounding the US and how it compared to the reality; and a comparison between the US in the past and at the time of the interviews.
    See also: Cowen, Maud; Gavin, Jimmy; Gelo, Grace; Harris, Shirley; Lewis, Ivan; Prescant, Becky; Richards, Evadni; Robinson, Irene; Saggese, Charles; Sutton, Kathleen; Unger, Margareta; and Ward, Katherine.
    Immigrants |x Cultural assimilation.
  - Interview Compilation for Radio Broadcast, Undated (Box Access Cassettes, Cassette 157, Box 75, Reel 333a - 333b)
    This recording contains a compilation of excerpts from interviews from and descriptions of the New York City Immigrant Oral History Project, as well as musical interludes. This compilation may have been created for a radio broadcast, but it is unclear if it was ever broadcasted. The volume and sound quality of the recording fluctuate between excerpts. The recording begins with an introduction to the project by Scott Weir, and an unidentified female interviewer explains that the recording addresses the experiences of three groups: Eastern European Jews; Italians; and African-American migrants from the southern United States (US). She notes that the excerpts reference the experiences of these groups in New York, New York; in factories; and in the formation of unions. She describes the social, economic, and political conditions that prompted many Eastern European Jews to immigrate to the US and interview excerpts follow discussing anti-Semitism, religious traditions, and education. Weir gives a brief history of Italian immigration to the US, and interview excerpts that follow discuss the economic contrast between landowners and agricultural laborers in Italy, and the fact that many Italians expected to return to Italy once they had enough money. The last section of the recording contains interview excerpts discussing the history of African Americans from Reconstruction to the 1970s; racial discrimination; the sequence of family migration; and ethnic relations among people in different New York City neighborhoods.
    See also: Fox, Abe; Robinson, Irene; Savio, Joseph; Unknown African-American Man; Wagner, Frank; Walters, [Unknown].
  - Introduction to Project, Undated (Box Access Cassettes, Cassette 183, Box 74, Reel 329a)
    Leon Fink, at the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union Local 22, explains that students in the Department of History at the City College of New York have undertaken a project to record the history of New York from the point of view of working people, specifically immigrants who came to the United States between 1900 and 1930. He lists specific questions that each interview will address and passes out a sign-up sheet for volunteers who want to be interviewed.
  - Ippolito, James and Stephanie, 1973 April 12 (Box Access Cassettes, Folder 145, Box 101, Box 98, Reel 909a, Box 1, Folder 44)
    James Ippolito was born in a small town in Sicily, Italy in 1910. He immigrated to the United States (US) in 1919 with his mother and two siblings. His father had immigrated to the US in 1912 and worked as a food peddler. The family lived in the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn, New York. Ippolito attended school through the eighth grade. He worked in a bed factory in the Greenpoint neighborhood of Brooklyn for a few years before getting a job in a furniture factory. He spent the bulk of his career in the furniture industry. He was a member of the United Furniture Workers of America (UFWA) Local 76 and was a shop steward in different factories between 1937-1965. He was a member of unspecified joint and executive boards and a trustee (the latter two likely UFWA Local 76). He married Stephanie Ippolito in 1936, with whom he had two sons. In 1962, the family moved from Williamsburg to the Ridgewood neighborhood of Queens.
    This interview was conducted by Joan Granucci and Martin Lesser on April 12, 1973 at James Ippolito's house in the Ridgewood neighborhood of Queens, New York. Ippolito's wife, Stephanie, participates in the interview. The interview covers Ippolito's immigration to the United States (US), his family, his working life, his union activity, his social activities, and his political affiliation. Ippolito discusses his family's staggered immigration to the US; his father's immigration seven years before the rest of the family; and his father's work to bring the rest of the family to the US. He discusses leaving school to join the workforce; working in a bed factory and being told he was too young for that type of work; and finding a job in the furniture industry through a friend. He recounts joining the United Furniture Workers of America Local 76; participating in strikes; and losing a job as a result of one of the strikes. He recounts working in a factory producing radio and television cabinets; switching to war production during World War II and making uniforms for the United States Army; and returning to production of television and radio cabinets after the war. He lists furniture plants in which he worked; the dates of his employment; and the types of furniture each produced. Ippolito and his wife describe the changes in the ethnic composition of the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn between the early 20th century and in the 1960s when they decided to move to Ridgewood. He lists social clubs to which belonged, including the Happy Hearts, and discusses support provided to the poor by the Democratic Party.
    Summary and index are available for this interview. An electronic transcript of this interview is also available by request.
    Furniture workers |z New York (State) |z New York |v Interviews.; United Furniture Workers of America
  - Jackson, [Unknown], 1973 April 16 (Box Access Cassettes, Cassette 185, Box 26, Reel 98a - 98b)
    The first name of the narrator is unknown. Mr. Jackson was born in Georgia and grew up in Daytona Beach, Florida. In 1921, he migrated to New York, New York, where he lived on 131st Street in the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan and married. He worked in multiple hotels in New York State and Atlantic City, New Jersey; in a dining car; and for the National Biscuit Company before he retired in 1966.